<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Consume a SOAP Web Service">
   <intro>
   		<description>Consume a SOAP Web Service by creating source and view models based on target WSDL file definition.<br/>
			<br/>
			<b>Note:</b> These steps are sequential and require you to complete or
			skip each step before being allowed to <b>Perform</b>, <b>Complete</b> or <b>Skip</b> the next step.<br/>
			<br/>
			To learn more about using cheat sheets click the help icon above.
			<br/>
			<br/>Press "<b>Click to Begin</b>" button below to start.
		</description>
   </intro>
   <item
         title="Create SOAP Connection Profile" skip="true">
      <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" param1="org.teiid.designer.connection.new.ws"/>
      <description>
         <b> This following action creates an ODA Web Service connection profile using the WSDL URL
         	 and end-point information.</b>
			<br/> ============================================================
			<br/> -- > Press "<b>Click to Perform</b>" button below to launch the wizard.
			<br/> -- > Inputs include: <b>WSDL URL</b> and sample <b>request/response document XML files</b> 
			<br/> -- > You may skip this step if you have already created a SOAP connection profile.
			<br/> ============================================================
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Generate Models" skip="true">
      <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			   pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" param1="org.teiid.designer.generatewsmodelsfromwsdl"/>
      <description>
         <b> This action utilizes the previously defined connection profile by interpreting the WSDL, 
         	locating any associated or dependent XML schema files, generating a physical model containing the required
         	invoke procedures for the service, and generating virtual models containing procedures which will build and 
         	parse the XML declared as the service messages.</b>
			<br/> ============================================================
			<br/> -- > Press "<b>Click to Perform</b>" button below to launch the model generator wizard.
			<br/> -- > Select your connection profile and press <b>Validate WSDL</b>.
			<br/> -- > Set the target folder or project location for your generated models and click <b>Next ></b>.
			<br/> -- > Select/de-select operations you wish to generate procedures for and click <b>Finish</b>.
			<br/> -- > Press "<b>Click to Complete</b>" button below when finished.
			<br/> -- > You may skip this step if you have already generated your models.
			<br/> ============================================================
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Create a VDB" skip="true">
      <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			   pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" param1="org.teiid.designer.vdb.create"/>
      <description>
         <b> Create a VDB containing your generated models.</b>
         	<br/> ============================================================
			<br/> -- > Press "<b>Click to Perform</b>" button below to launch <b>New VDB</b> wizard.
			<br/> -- > Enter a name for your VDB and click <b>Finish</b> to create the VDB and open in editor.
			<br/> -- > In the VDB editor, use the add models button to add models from your workspace.
			<br/> -- > You may skip this step if you have already created a VDB.
			<br/> ============================================================
      </description>
   </item>   
   <item
         title="Test your VDB" skip="true">
      <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			   pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" param1="org.teiid.designer.vdb.execute"/>
      <description>
         <b> Execute your VDB by deploying to a running Teiid server, creating a JDBC connection to that VDB, opening
         a SQL Scrapbook Editor and executing queries against your VDB.</b>
            <br/> ============================================================
			<br/> -- > Press "<b>Click to Perform</b>" button below to launch the wizard.
			<br/> -- > Browse and select your VDB from your workspace and click <b>OK</b>.
			<br/> -- > The Data Source Explorer perspective will be activated.
			<br/> -- > A SQL Scrapbook editor will be opened using the generated VDB's JDBC connection.
			<br/> -- > Follow the instructions in the scrapbook to perform ad-hoc queries.
			<br/> -- > You may skip this step if you have already created a VDB.
			<br/> ============================================================
      </description>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>