<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Create Model from Flat File Source">
   <intro>
   		<description>This cheat sheet shows you how to create a model from a flat file source.
		</description>
   </intro>
   
   <item title="Create New Teiid Model Project" skip="true">
     <description>
         <b> Follow the steps below to create a Teiid Model Project</b>
      </description>
      <subitem label="Launch New Teiid Model Project Wizard" skip="true">
            <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
            pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" 
            param1="org.teiid.designer.newProjectCommand"/> 
      </subitem>
      <subitem skip="true">
          <description>
                      <b>1)</b> Specify unique project name
                <br/> <b>2)</b> Click <b>Next ></b> twice to get to <b>Model Project Options</b> page
                <br/> <b>3)</b> Check folders you wish the wizard to create in your project
                <br/> <b>4)</b> Click <b>Finish</b>
          </description>
      </subitem>
   </item>

   <item title="Create New Flat File Source Connection" skip="true">
      	<description>
         	<b> Follow the steps below to create a Teiid Flat File Connection profile</b>
      	</description>
         <subitem label="Launch New Flat File Source Connection Wizard" skip="true">
      			<action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" 
			param1="org.teiid.designer.connection.new.flatfile"/>
   		</subitem>
   		<subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
	                  <b>1)</b> Specify unique name and optional description and click <b>Next &gt;</b>
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Browse to select local file folder or enter file folder URL
				<br/> <b>3)</b> Select desired options and click <b>Finish</b>
	      </description>
   	  </subitem>
   </item>
   
   <item title="Create Source From Flat File Connection" skip="true">
      	<description>
         	<b> Follow the steps below to create a relational model by importing table data via a Flat File connection profile</b>
      	</description>
         <subitem label="Launch Import Flat File Source Wizard" skip="true">
      			<action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" 
			param1="org.teiid.designer.importFlatFileCommand"/>
   		</subitem>
   		<subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
	                  <b>1)</b> Select your <b>Data File Source</b> (connection profile)
				<br/> <b>2)</b> The <b>Available Data Files</b> section will show your source file location and list
				    your source text files
				<br/> <b>3)</b> Select a file as your source
				<br/> <b>4)</b> Browse to select your target source model location and enter unique name. Click <b>Next &gt;</b>
				<br/> <b>5)</b> Specify your file data format as <b>Character delimited</b> or <b>Fixed width</b>. <b>Next &gt;</b>
	      </description>
   	   </subitem>
   	   <subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
	      		<b>Character Delimited Parser Settings Option</b>
	      		<br/> The primary purpose of this importer is to help you create a view table containing the 
	      			transformation required to query the user-defined data file. This page presents a number 
	      			of options you can use to customize the <b>Generated SQL Statement</b>
	            <br/> <b>1)</b> Specify header options (Column names in header, header line number and first data line number)
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Parse selected row, changed character delimiter and edit the TEXTTABLE() function options.
				<br/> <b>3)</b> If columns names are not defined in a file header or if you wish to modify or 
					create custom columns, you can use the <b>ADD, DELETE, UP, DOWN</b> to manage the column info 
					in your SQL.
				<br/> --- NOTE: To aid in determining if your parser settings are correct you can select a data row 
					in your File Contents Preview section and click the <b>Parse Selected Row button</b>. A dialog will
					 be displayed showing the list of columns and the resulting column data. If your column data 
					 is not what you expected, you'll need to adjust your settings accordingly.
				<br/> <b>4)</b> Click <b>Next &gt;</b>
	      </description>
   	   </subitem>
   	   <subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
	      		<b>Fixed Column Width Parser Settings Option</b>
	      		<br/> <b>1)</b> Use the <b>File Contents Preview</b> to analyze your column data format
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Enter your first data line number in the <b>Format Options</b> section.
				<br/> <b>3)</b> Use the <b>Cursor Position</b> and <b>Text Length</b> value (for selected text) to assist in determing
					the data column width values in the <b>Column Information</b> in the lower right. 
				<br/> <b>4)</b> If columns names are not defined in a file header or if you wish to modify or create custom columns, 
					you can use the ADD, DELETE, UP, DOWN to manage the column info in your SQL.
				<br/> <b>5)</b> Set appropriate <b>TEXTTABLE()</b> function options
				<br/> <b>6)</b> Click <b>Next &gt;</b>
	      </description>
   	   </subitem>
   		<subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
	      		<b>View Model Definition</b>
	            <br/> <b>1)</b> Select the target folder location where your new view model will be created
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Enter unique view model name
				<br/> --- Note the Model Status section which will indicate the validity of the model name, 
					whether the model exists or not. Lastly, enter a unique, valid view table name.
				<br/> <b>4)</b> Click <b>Finish</b> to generate your models
	      </description>
   	   </subitem>
   	   
   	   
   </item>
   
   
   <item title="Test Flat File Data" skip="true">
      	<description>
         	<b> Follow the steps below to preview data from your newly generated Flat File view table.</b>
      	</description>
         <subitem label="Launch Preview Data Dialog" skip="true">
      			<action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" 
			param1="org.teiid.designer.previewData"/>
   		</subitem>
   		<subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
	                  <b>1)</b> Click the browse <b>"..."</b> button to select the newly created view table
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Click OK to execute the query
				<br/> <b>3)</b> Results of the query will displayed in the SQL Results view
	      </description>
   	  </subitem>
   </item>
   
   <item title="Create VDB" skip="true">
     <description>
         <b>Follow the steps below to create a new VDB</b>
      </description>
      <subitem label="Launch New VDB Wizard" skip="true">
            <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" 
			param1="org.teiid.designer.vdb.create"/> 
      </subitem>
      <subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
				      <b>1)</b> Select <b>"..."</b> button to browse and select project or folder location.
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Enter a unique name for your VDB
				<br/> <b>3)</b> Enter an optional description for your VDB
				<br/> <b>4)</b> Select the <b>Add</b> button to choose models to go in your VDB
				<br/> <b>5)</b> Click <b>Finish</b>
      	  </description>
   	  </subitem>
   </item>
   
   
   <item title="Test VDB" skip="true">
     <description>
         <b>Follow the steps below to test the VDB</b>
      </description>
      <subitem label="Launch Execute VDB Dialog" skip="true">
            <action class="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui.actions.LaunchDesignerCommandAction" 
			pluginId="org.teiid.designer.advisor.ui" 
			param1="org.teiid.designer.vdb.execute"/> 
      </subitem>
      <subitem skip="true" >
	      <description>
				      <b>1)</b> Select <b>"..."</b> button to browse and select a VDB.
				<br/> <b>2)</b> Click OK to deploy VDB and open connection in Data Source Explorer
				<br/> <b>3)</b> Follow instructions in open SQL Scrapbook Editor
				<br/> <b>4)</b> View your query results in the SQL Results view
      	  </description>
   	  </subitem>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>