<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<cheatsheet title="Overview of Web Services">

	<intro 
		contextId="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.cheatSheetHelp">
		<description>This cheat sheet will provide information about Web services
			and how they work in this product.<br/>
			<br/>
			<b>Note:</b> These steps are sequential and require you to complete or
			skip each step before being allowed to <b>Perform</b>, <b>Complete</b> or <b>Skip</b> the next step.<br/>
			<br/>
			To learn more about using cheat sheets click help icon above.
			<br/>
			<br/>Press "<b>Click to Begin</b>" button below to start this cheat sheet.
		</description>
	</intro>

	<item
		contextId="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.structureOfWebServiceHelp"
		title="Structure of a Web Service">
		<description>
            MetaMatrix Web services are <b>data services</b> - they connect relational 
		    or XML data sources to XML output.   While they may be created in different ways,
		    all MetaMatrix Web services share some common features:
			<br/>
			
			<br/><b>1.</b> One or more <b>Relational Sources</b> that describe where the data
			    is coming from.
			<br/>
			<br/><b>2.</b> <b>XSD Schemas</b> defining the XML formats for the Web service operation's 
			input and output arguments.  These will comprise the bodies of the request and response
			 SOAP messages when the Web service is executed.
			<br/>
			<br/><b>3.</b> An <b>XML View Model</b> that describes the relationship between the 
			XML format of the Web service operation's output argument and the Relational Source models.
			<br/>
			<br/><b>4.</b> A <b>Web service Model</b> that names the Web service and defines the 
			individual Web service operations.  Each Web service operation is linked to the input 
			XML Schema, the output XML Schema, and the output XML View model.
			<br/>
			<br/><b>5.</b> A <b>WSDL</b> (Web Services Description Language) file that describes 
			    the interface to the users of the Web service.
			<br/>
			<br/>Press "<b>Click to Complete</b>" button below to read the next step.
		</description>
	</item>

	<item
		title="Source materials">
		<!--action class="com.metamatrix.modeler.internal.ui.actions.ImportAction" 
			pluginId="com.metamatrix.modeler.ui" /-->
		<description>Web services can be created from different starting points.
			You will need one or more of the following pieces of information:
			<br/>
			<br/><b>1.</b> <b>Source Connection Information</b>
			<br/><b>2.</b> <b>XSD Schemas</b>
			<br/><b>3.</b> <b>WSDL files</b>
			<br/>
			<br/>Press "<b>Click to Complete</b>" button below to read the next step.
		</description>
	</item>

	<item
		title="Create Web Service">
		<description>Click one of the following icons to open help for working
			with that type of data.
			<br/><b>Note:</b> If you do not see any steps here, be sure to complete
			all previous steps.</description>
		<subitem label="Relational Data Sources">
			<action class="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.actions.LaunchCheatSheetAction" 
				pluginId="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui" 
				param1="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.cheat.JDBCToWebService"/>
		</subitem>
		<subitem label="XSD Schema or XML Views">
			<action class="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.actions.LaunchCheatSheetAction" 
				pluginId="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui" 
				param1="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.cheat.XSDToWebService"/>
		</subitem>
		<subitem label="WSDL files">
			<action class="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.actions.LaunchCheatSheetAction" 
				pluginId="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui" 
				param1="com.metamatrix.modeler.webservice.ui.cheat.WSDLToWebService"/>
		</subitem>
	</item>
</cheatsheet>
