<!--
 # JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source.
 # Copyright (C) 2008 Red Hat, Inc.
 # Copyright (C) 2000-2007 MetaMatrix, Inc.
 # Licensed to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor
 # license agreements.  See the copyright.txt file in the
 # distribution for a full listing of individual contributors.
 #
 # This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
 # modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
 # License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
 # version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
 #
 # This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 # but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 # MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
 # Lesser General Public License for more details.
 
 # You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
 # License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
 # Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
 # 02110-1301 USA.
-->
<contexts>
	<context id="namespaceResolutionPage">
		<description>This wizard page shows all selected WSDL(s) and their referenced namespaces. You can resolve namespaces to existing resources in your workspace or from the file system. Click the "Workspace..." button to choose files from the workspace. Click "File System..." to choose them from the file system. Selected namespaces can be viewed, have their information copied to the clipboard, or made unresolved using the toolbar buttons. Also, another toolbar button can be used to display a namespace dependency dialog. All namespaces must be resolved to continue.</description>
	</context>
	<context id="schemaLocationPage">
		<description>This wizard page allows you to maintain location information about the schemas output to your workspace. Select a row in the table and then edit it's information in the editor at the bottom of the page.</description>
	</context>
	<context id="schemaLocationPage_schemaLocationEditor">
		<description>This editor is used to modify the name and location of output schema files. Select a folder in your workspace by clicking the browse button. Type in a file name that doesn't match an existing XSD file. Click the Apply button to accept changes.</description>
	</context>
	<context id="wsdlSelectionPage">
		<description>This wizard page allows you to choose existing WSDL(s) which will be used to generate the WSDL model. Click the "Workspace..." button to choose WSDL(s) from the workspace. Click "File System..." to choose them from the file system. Selected WSDL(s) can be viewed, removed from the list, or have their information copied to the clipboard using the toolbar buttons.</description>
	</context>
	<context id="xmlModelSelectionPage">
		<description>This wizard page allows you to optionally create an XML document model with your WSDL model. Choose a workspace location by using the browse button. Then type a model name that doesn't already exist at that location. If you don't want an XML model created just deselect the checkbox. Click "Finish" to create the model(s).</description>
	</context>
</contexts>
